What do you think Where do people live better in
Как вы считаете Где люди живут лучше в
Russia or in the United States of
России или в Соединённых Штатах
America on
Америки на
Baikal on Baikal is better than in the
Байкале на Байкале лучше чем в
United States of America Yes
Соединённых Штатах Америки Да
exactly
точно
Hello Hello Where are you from?
Здравствуйте Здравствуйте Вы откуда
grandfather from the
дедушка из
village grandfather from the village understood how you
деревни деду из деревни понял как вы
grandfather from the village feel about the fact that
дедушка из деревни относитесь к тому что
Russia attacked Ukraine
Россия напала на Украину
about when in what month In what year everything
о когда в каком месяце В каком году всё
grandpa was diagnosed then this
дедушка диагноз поставлен тогда такой
question grandpa Do you think Where do people
вопрос дедушка Как вы считаете Где люди
live better in Russia or in the United
живут лучше в России или в Соединённых
States of
Штатах
America on
Америки на
Baikal on Baikal is better than in the
Байкале на Байкале лучше чем в
United States of America Yes, exactly, I’m
Соединённых Штатах Америки Да точно м
interested in saying how much
интересно можете сказать сколько
the salary is on Baikal  and how much in the
зарплата на Байкале и сколько в
United States of
Соединённых Штатах
America I
Америки я
see I can’t
вижу не
the salary is united
зарплата соедин
w The United States of America is, well, it’s like
ш Соединённые Штаты Америки это ну как
life with different republics and in each state
быте с разные республики и в каждых штах
the pay and for each job is a different salary
плата и на каждой работе разная зарплата
you are
тебя что интересует
interested in I’m interested in, for example,
интересует Меня интересует например
look at Lake Baikal in the Russian
смотрите на Байкале в Российской
Federation and in  poor state of the
Федерации и в самом бедном штате
United States of America Where
Соединённых Штатов Америки Где выше
the salary is higher, well, tell me the poorest state of the
зарплата ну назови мне самый бедный штат
United States of America Okay Let's
Соединённых Штатах Америки О'кей Давайте
take for example the state of Alabama and compare
возьмём например штат алабаму сравним
it with Baikal in Russia where the salary is higher
его с байкалом в России где больше
and what is the salary in relation to what is the
а в чём зарплата по отношению к чему
relationship here we need
отношени здесь нужно
in relation to each other  friend, here is
отношение по отношению друг к другу вот
the salary in the USA and the salary in Russia, their
зарплата в США и зарплата в России ихние
attitude No, you need the center of
отношение Нет нужно нужно центр
relativity and
относительности а
then take Baikal and connected
потом это брать Байкал и соединён
America, these are three
Америки этот это три
unknowns, one One must be
неизвестных одна Одно должно быть
known, don’t roll your eyes, I understand, I understand,
известное ты не лупи глаза понял я понял
look at the known Let’s see the
смотрите известное Давайте посмотрим
known, let’s take an iPhone brand phone
известное возьмём телефон марки iPhone
how much  you need to work on Lake Baikal and
сколько нужно работать на Байкале и
how much is needed in the state of Alabama to
сколько нужно в штате Алабама чтобы
earn money on an
заработать на
iPhone? Are you iPhones? Where are they
iPhone Ты что ли Айфоны Где
making them
делают на
in Taiwan?
станки на Тайване откуда
Taiwan
Тайваня
she The United States of America doesn't
она Соединённых Штатах Америки земли не
have enough land why did they send machines to Taiwan
хватает зачем они на Тайвань отправили
labor force cheaper for example
рабочая сила дешевле например
we signed an agreement let's supply the
пове заключали договор да м поставим
machines And you will sell it to us at a
станки А вы нам будете продавать это по
low
низкой
price
цене
So okay let's take the kids to the
Так ладно давай так дет смотри возьмём в
USA and Lake Baikal Yes, here is the state of Alabama  and
США и на Байкале Да вот штат Алабама и
Baikal Siberia where with his salary a
Байкал Сибирь где на свою зарплату
person can drink gasoline food telephone
Челове сможет пить бензина еды телефоно
everything you imagine
всего ты представляешь
Russia is an energy seller energy seller
Россия - это продавец энергии продавец
where is the energy Look, let's do
энергии где энергия Вот ты смотри давай
the opposite where is the lowest
наоборот где самая низкая
energy the cheapest energy Let's go to the
энергия самая дешёвая энергия Давай на
sun you've also climbed on Mars on Mars it's
солнце ты ещ на Мар залез на Марсе она
not cheap
не дешёвая
here on our land here in our country Where is the
вот на нашей земле вот у нас Где самое
lowest price of electricity in the United
низкое электричество цена Соединённых
States of
Штатах
America
Америки
How much in relation to wages Let's
Почём по отношению к зарплате Давайте
look at the relationship Well,
посмотрим по отноше какое отношение Ну
let's go on, how much is your electricity on Lake Baikal?
давайте Вот давай почём у вас на Байкале
ruble 20 is
электроэнергия рубль 20
this in dollars,
это в долларах
how much is it in dollars about cent cent and more
сколько это в долларах о цент цент и ещё
30 there 1.2 cents
30 там 1,2 цента
yes
да
1 Well 3 cents let it be that way and in
1 Ну 3 цента пускай так будет а в
America in the state of Alabama electricity is
Америке в штате Алабама электроэнергия
0.89 cents cheaper Show So show You
0,89 цента дешевле Покажи Так покажи Ты
show me where 1.2 Show
мне покажи где 1,2 покажи
Go to Google look So you also
Залезь в Google посмотри Так ты тоже
look Go to
посмотри Залезь в
Google Well come on  I'll climb in
Google Ну давай Я залезу Давай
Come on, let me now let me climb into
давай я сейчас те Давай я тебе залезу в
Google for you I'll climb into Google for you now Well,
Google я тебе сейчас залезу в Google Ну
come on, you can do it faster Yes, I'm
давай ты быстрее можешь делать Да я
fast, I'm nimble I have here this
быстрый я шустрый У меня есть тут это
Google voice assistant
голосовой помощник Гугла
Yes, now, and I'll check you,
Да сейчас а я а я тебя проверю
Come on now We'll check you
Давай сейчас Мы тебя
Grandfather, in short, now we’ll tell you the state of
дед короче сейчас мы тебе скажем штат
Alabama I’m from the state of Alabama I
Алабама Я же сам со штата Алабама Я же
know Alabama does
знаю Алабама киловатт электричества
n’t supply a kilowatt of electricity Listen, it doesn’t supply
о не подаёт Слушай не подаёт
it Well, you give it Well, come on now Take a guess, let’s say you’re
се ну ты даёшь ну давай сейчас Посри
ready to listen
давай что готов слушать
Come on
Давай
Hello Google tell Uh, what is the price of
Алло Google скажи Э какова цена
electricity in the state of
электричества в штате
Alabama Alabama  the price of a kilowatt of
Алабама Алабама цена киловатта
electricity is
электричества
0.89
0,89
cents Please repeat again what is the
цента Ещё раз повтори пожалуйста какова
price of electricity in the state of
цена электричества в штате
Alabama I answer in the state of Alabama the price of a
Алабама отвечаю в штате Алабама цена
kilowatt of electricity is
киловатта электричество
0.89 cents in Russia on Lake Baikal
0,89 цента у тебя в России на Байкале
1.2 cents is 0.89 cents cheaper and
1,2 цента это 0,89 центов дешевле в
one and a half times cheaper than
полтора раза чем у
yours  in one second Well, okay, I agree,
тебя в в одну вторую Ну ладно я согласен
yes, you know why, look, we have a
да А знаешь почему смотри у нас очень
lot of alternative
много альтернативных источников
energy sources, we have wind turbines in Alabama
энергетики у нас же ветряки во алабаме
Yes, we have electricians
стоят Да у нас вот это электрика вообще
for free, we even do it when
на халяву у нас даже сдела вот когда
these hurricanes come, Tornadoes, and the bigger the
идут эти ураганы Торнадо да чем больше
hurricane  the more windmills generate
ураган тем больше ветряки наматывают
electricity, the more the Virgo
электроэнергии она тем более более Дева
melts, moreover, we generate so much
стаёт больше того у нас столько
electricity there is a month,
вырабатывается электроэнергии есть месяц
it’s called the muso season, you know what
вот называется сезон мусов знаешь что
muso is, tropical
мусо тропические такие
winds like this are not winds, this is the movement of air
ветра не ветра это перемещение воздуха
Well, yes, the wind is the movement of air
Ну да ветер это есть перемещение воздуха
Yes,
Да так вот
look at the mass of air -  this is the monsoon
смотри масса воздуха - это и есть мусон
ok
о'кей
ok super so here’s the question More precisely not a
О'кей супер так вот вопрос Точнее не
question But the trick is when it comes This is the
вопрос А фишка когда идёт Вот это
monsoon movement of air masses of air
муссоны перемещение воздуха масс воздуха
Yes windmills generate so much energy
Да ветряки настолько много энергии
That manufacturers can’t do
вырабатывают Что производители не могут
it Yes they sort it out so in some
её Да перебирают поэтому в некоторые
months there is, look at the season  monsoons,
месяцы вот есть смотри в сезон муссонов
we are even paid extra for using
нам даже доплачивают за употребление
electricity because so that we
электроэнергии потому что чтобы мы
pump out its excess, you
выкачали её излишки
understand why I need to pump it out as
понимаешь зачем зачем мне её выкачивать
much as I need, that’s what I
сколько мне нужно столько я и
consume Yes, but for example, look, they ask
потребляю Да но например смотри просят
us, for example, if you turn on the lighting at night,
нас например если ты включаешь на ночь
for example, Yes, you turn on
например ещё освещение Да ты включаешь
some electrical appliances for  in order to
какие-то электроприборы для того чтобы
burn out more electricity during the
выпалить больше электроэнергии в сезон
monsoon season when it can’t be
муссонов когда она ветряк не можно
stopped so easily, it
остановить так просто он он всё он
starts to generate so much energy, there’s
начинает столько вырабатывает энергии её
nowhere to put it, and we get paid extra for
некуда девать и нам доплачивают за её
using it, even for this one
использование даже вот этот один
month we don’t get paid extra, we also power
месяц нам не доплачивают мы питаем ещё
Mongolia Mongolia because Mongolia is
Монголию Монголию потому что Монголия
before  Baikal wanted to install a
перед байкалом хотела ставить
power plant, we dissuaded them and
электростанцию мы их отговорили и
made
сделали
payments to all the Mongols and
оплату всем монголам и и
ourselves. You see, look, let's go back
себе то Видишь Смотри то давай вернёмся
to our question:
к нашему вопросу
where can a resident buy more electricity for his
где житель может больше купить за свою
salary in the state of Alabama
зарплату электроэнергии в штате Алабама
or in Baikal, how much is your salary
или в на Байкале сколько у вас зарплата
on Baikal, we will now calculate how much
на Байкале мы сейчас посчитаем сколько
kilowatt Your salary How much electricity can you
киловатт Твоя зарплата Сколько ты можешь
buy, how much is the salary
электроэнергии купить сколько зарплата
on Baikal children Well, I have 200 rubles a
на Байкале дет Ну я у меня 200 руб в
month, 2300 rubles salary How much a
месяц идёт 2300 руб зарплата Сколько у
person’s salary I don’t know, I don’t work,
человека зарплату я не знаю я не работаю
I’m retired Let’s calculate with you the
я на пенсии Давай посчитаем с у вас
minimum salary is 19,000 rubles 19,000
минимальная зарплата 19.000 руб 19.000
rubles is correct
руб правильно
not a little little you take a little you take a little you don’t take
не мало мало берёшь мало берёшь не она
it that’s the official minimum wage it’s
так это официальная минимальная зарплата
not you who think wrong but I
не ты неправильно считаешь а я правильно
think correctly look if you think
считаю смотри если ты считаешь
wrong I won’t call you not
неправильно я тебя буду называть не Сам
Look yourself let’s divide 19,000 by
смотри давай делим 19.000 на
0.1 012 dollars Yes this is the price per kilowatt
0,1 012 доллара Да это цена за киловатта
per kilowatt it turns out  that you don’t really
за киловатт получается что ты не вообще
care how much you get How many more times
дофига у вас получается Сколько ещё раз
how much A ruble Yes you have a ruble Wait
сколько А рубль Да рубль у тебя Подожди
19,000 Yes we divide by uh ruble 20 yes
19.000 Да делим на э рубль 20 да
it turns out that for the minimum wage
получается во на минимальную зарплату
a Russian on Lake Baikal can buy 15,000
россиянин на Байкале может купить 15.000
Irkutsk region how much Come on How much is
Иркутской области сколько Давай Сколько
the salary in the Irkutsk region
зарплата в Иркутской области
Ivanovo Irkutsk exactly  19 Yes, you’re right,
Ивановская Иркутская точно 19 Да ты прав
I’m right, you got it, I’ll call you
я ж прав Ты понял я тебя буду называть
because you’re so
за то что ты так
aggressive, you see, look, it’s
агрессивный видишь Видишь Смотри так вот
19,000, and we divide it by the price of a kilowatt,
19.000 да делим на цену киловатта
1.2 rubles, it turns out
1,2 рубля получается
15.33 kW, you can only buy it in
15.33 кВт можешь купить только а в
the state in the Irkutsk region.
штате в Иркутской области
According to the source, your Irkuts  Ministry of Labor, the
Согласно источнику твой иркутс минтруд
average salary in the Irkutsk
средняя заработная плата в Иркутской
region increased to
области выросла до
71 Look, not the average, but the median, ask the
71 Смотри не среднюю а медиан ную спроси
median
медиан ную
salary, the median,
зарплату медиан ную спроси медиан ную
ask the median salary, ask, not the average, the
зарплату спроси а не среднюю медиан ную
average, it’s the governor’s billion Yes, and
средняя это у губернатора миллиард Да а
everyone else in the ruble, ask the
все у всех остальных по рублю спроси
median salary grandfather
медиан ную зарплату дед
Let's ask grandfather for the minimum median
Давай проси дед минималь медиану
salary of the region Come on, you're afraid
зарплату области Давай ты же боишься
Come on,
Давай де
71,000 look at Look, say not the
71.000 на смотри на Смотри скажи не
average median salary is
средняя медианная зарплата
1000 Tell her, give it the median salary
1000 скажи ей давай медиан ную зарплату
Come on
Давай
grandfather And ask how much a kilowatt of
дед А спроси сколько у вас киловатт
electricity
электроэнергии
costs you, ask in a voice Let's
стоит спроси вот голосом Давай
give it up now Now
сейчас брошу Сейчас
give me the size of
давай размер
honey
меда
so a kilowatt
так киловатт
of electricity in the Irkutsk
электроэнергии в Иркутской
[music]
[музыка]
region According to the source Ifa Def
области Согласно источнику Ифа Def
rus.ru
rus.ru
ru then you see you still you on you understood you
ру то ты видишь ты ещё ты на ты понял ты
you said ruble 20 and ruble 40 you ruble 20
ты сказал рубль 20 а рубль 40 ты руб 20
you you deceive
ты ты обману
you let me
ты давай
write everything to my Telegram directly at once axis
всё пись на мий Telegram прямо зараз ось
VN
ВН
apok tse more and more respectfully YouTube occupying
апок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube заня
us through skarg Orcs in your ban and even
нас через скарг Орки в твый бан и дуже
more videos don’t show people immediately don’t
багато видео не показуе людям вчасно не
show information about streams Tom for this
показуе информация про стрими Тому для
purpose, Mali operational link ppi
того щоб ми Мали оперативный звязок ппи
right now and while there in telegra okm
прямо зараз а пок там в телегра окм
video sche tezh tsikava  and korisna information
видео ще теж цикава и корисна информация
and we are responsible for you trimati postiyny
и ми повинни з вами тримати постийний
operational link
оперативный звязок
nezalezhno in that chi show you the process
незалежно в того чи покаже вам проце
YouTube Glory to Ukraine letter
YouTube Слава Украине пись
with
с